you I'm going to kick it off we have
three talks uh uh this one is about what
I learn about you know from get up
co-pilot to AI native development it's a
talk that I've given already a few times
it will be a quick talk hopefully uh I'm
still on a jack lag I'm from Belgium I
just flew all the way in so it's
probably past midnight right now for me
uh so you know I'll get it over with or
am I um my name is Patrick De um some of
you might know me from the word devops
um uh it was also something that I
started with 60 people in the room in
20 2009 in Belgium and this LEDs to the
movement of devops as we know it I'm not
saying this will happen here the same
but hey amazing things can happen just
from a Meetup and getting the right
people um quter on the dev's handbook I
tried to be industry neutral uh not like
work for a specific vendor that's why I
like this community I can talk whatever
tool whatever I like I used to be
obviously def SE cops and for two years
I've been very focused on gen um gen and
the product and are more and more
recently doing engineering work with AI
so that's also what led to this event as
well I'm trying to get make sense of
this world and uh as you you know as we
go through the presentation I have a few
blocks one of it is that we're seeing
these tools doing coding for us which I
call delegated coding we're moving away
from the nitty-gritty specifying the
exact call that we want to do and moving
up to more
specifications we hope that the system
works so well uh that we can delegate
the trust but it has to earn our trust
first um and we're feeding it way more
data that's our codebase that's our
slack or Zoom meetings like obviously
what I learned now in two years of
dealing with AI if there's a problem you
probably solve it with more AI so
there's a flywheel of kind of
like like believing that eventually
we'll solve this into a good way and
last is that we actually keep that human
oversight because we don't want to have
the machines run away without us being
able to do and when things fail we still
have to be able to deal with things um
that happen so the first
part we all seen get up tapt go autoc
completion on steroids right that's
where it all started uh that's probably
what's been sold the most into
Enterprises co-pilot heay we got like
tick in the box and we're there I think
obviously that it doesn't stop there yes
we got chat but everybody has chat now
in their Windows right like copy and
paste and uh this used to be very clunky
hey you know ask chat GPT copy and paste
it in now it we get way better we get
things like instant apply this is from
cursor like it was generated which they
applied this to the code which is
already a step up of us not having to
copy and paste it can even start
predicting when we do a change where's
the next place our cursor needs to be so
the tab is not just the completion but
it's like jumping around in the editor
where we think the next edit should
happen so it's already a step up from
that order completion as
well like instead of just only autoc
completion we now have reasoning models
added to the mix so it's thinking things
through it's making a plan of attack on
how to do things it's not any more
simple code completion in
there then you know we've initially we
thought oh you're still from our code
and then there was a whole discussion at
GitHub like you know who copied what
from whom um ironically enough the big
companies were all complaining like you
can't index our stuff but guess what
biggest companies were all asking well
can you please train things how we do
things um and you know eventually we got
into more local uh codebase indexing
because fine tuning was too hard and
that was kind of like a middle ground
that was really you know useful to do
things
things instead of generating a code
snippet changing one files we got to
multiple files editing um it was really
you know a game changer not having to do
kind of the different things uh step by
step but all of a sudden and then we
start a new kind of set of problems that
we needed to review so many of the
generated code uh all the
time we learned that we could add
context not just from our code but it
could red deter
so whatever error is on the terminal we
can feed it back to the code generation
in the chat that was another step up and
the same thing is happening with the
browser like you can read the browser
errors he can read like whatever is
happening so it becomes eventually one
big feedback loop uh of systems um yes
you know of course we want to generate
tests because we were really bad at
generating tests but tests are awesome
and will help us in the future guess
what actually AI is very useful to write
tests because it always wants to change
things and if you don't have tests we
don't know what it has changed too much
so more and more it was not about just
the code generation but it was also
about the test generation and helping
that uh
improved I mentioned the continuous loop
um you know Devin it will come up uh
today a few times it was a big spark it
will take your job away blah blah blah
it's not that important the fact is that
they were the maybe the first ones who
are articulated a little bit at that
feedback loop that I just described in
one two where you can kind of get
everything going and uh combined
together and then if you could take it
like one step further why have one agent
why not have multiple agents working on
the same code base again I don't see
many people do that today but there's
some through to that that maybe you know
we're able to do this in a parallel
universe when the tools actually get
better
wanted to bring this out um you know
we've focused a lot of code generation
uh agents doing stuff but here's an
example of something that takes your
code put it into production and actually
Auto optimizes the code based on
production feedback right so this is a
like an AB testing tool so we're
extending the loop not just in our inner
Dev Loop to things that come from
production so this was all about code
generation as such now the next kind of
Step Up is the code Centric from to
specification um if you use uh composer
in critor you start getting into that
continuous loop of prompting you don't
write the code anymore if you don't like
it you say a follow-up prompt uh and you
type less and less about the code you
just steer it into the direction that
you want
this um we've seen simple examples of
people providing a markdown file in
their coding and they say at
specification MD do these things so
we're kind of reusing the intent of what
we want and not just in the prompting
but we save this as almost like a
specification in there so we're getting
towards what giab called towards intent
based coding so it's not about the code
good ghost text it's not about the chat
it's about kind of having a spec that
gets coded according to plan uh that we
end up for um I'll skip this
um then we also have uh coding
identities where you can say I'm a
python developer I like this rules I am
a react I have these rules so part of
this goes into the specification on how
you want things
done um you can add these roles now to
your project um for this project I want
this roles for that project I want that
rules so people can reuse this almost
like reusable prompts reusable
specifications uh in your projects
already and we haven't talked about
design because you can also upload an
image and say implement the UI the front
end with according to this image so it's
not a way of specifying things not in
text not in a prompt but by providing an
image and then you breaks down into a
whole plan and I don't know what
happened there but um you start seeing
new tooling coming around that actually
start thinking like why don't we just
manage product requirements that
documents and then coding will
eventually come from that we're not
there yet technology wise but if you
take break this down into like smaller
pieces of requirements that is
definitely something that we can do
today um and so you get into that more
specification Centric instead of code
Centric working as a Dev
developer and then the interesting thing
will become when I change the
specification my code will change I
change my code specification will change
so that bir directional kind of spec to
code code to spec uh will be an
interesting way of doing this so this is
where the co-pilots and others uh
Amazons they're all thinking towards
this direction that you're starting to
specify this uh instead of having to do
the the detailed
coding now this was specification
um the next thing I want to show is that
we're having an explosion of context
that we added the whole workspace cannot
be added it's not one file that gets
indexed uh here's an example of adding
an external code Library just as context
to be reused in your own code um very
simple to add um then we started adding
documentation sources because
documentation is awesome so why don't we
reuse that that right why why would do
we trust the llms to to uh kind of make
up the things when we have the most
current version of documentation
available and we can point to that uh of
what we're doing uh so we start having
more of these um so context is context
aware and we're just going to see this
more and more explode in our
tooling we even start optimizing
documentation to become usable as
context so much like SEO is op like
optimizing a website or documentation
will be optimized for adding being added
as a context to the
systems and then we can bring in open
tatry information as more context of
what is happening in production should I
touch this uh kind of function oh no
it's being used like a million times the
last couple of days you should probably
take care of this right like that that
kind of context is going to be super
useful to this and then if you think
about more and more of this context
being
generated uh this is a nice example of
Devon whether it works or not is you
start feeding it more documentation more
context and all of a sudden says I think
this is important let me save this as
knowledge because then I can reuse this
you benefit from keeping this as
knowledge described and I benefit as an
AI to use this for my next Generation so
kind of that moves from documentation
more context to knowledge
and then you can keep a memory like
first I did this then I did that so you
kind of keep track of the specification
uh this tend to work better than feeding
in a big specification that you have
like small steps of incremental buildup
of your specification there as
well now when we have a that information
we have that knowledge why don't we have
the agents also use this to respond to
pull requests because now we generate
code we send the pool request now the
agent can use all the context we feeded
it to actually reply to people who
having questions about this so there's
an auto engage function that we can use
there now next part is you got the
context we got the specs we got the cjun
how is it going to win our
trust AI is still and will be an AI slot
machine like we we can't actually
control always that good at what it
generates but you start working around
this uh in many
ways right so if you generate
code like first you can check maybe the
lenser is working that's great that's
good feedback but will actually run
right so you start seeing systems that
actually take your code behind the
scenes they start running it see if it
actually compiles and runs so that kind
of Shadow Way of working of your editor
has a Shadow environment that it works
with as a runability check in
there and when it changes something it
will verify also whether it maybe like
uh did something to the documentations
that's not all data so it's giving us
feedback of what it did what the impact
was so that's how it's starting to gain
our trust in a way that it it makes us
aware of what the thing that it was
doing we can even think about like the
code that was
generated Like You could argue what good
and bad code is but for example we could
trace how complex the code is can a
human still understand the code like we
don't want like long and long files so
we can keep a check on this uh we can
kind of put this as quality metrics so
that kind of gains us trust if it feeds
uh if it passes these tests that it's
actually a better Cod being generated
obviously we can go into security
testing with tread modeling um probably
later some verified ref factoring we
could do uh what are you know whatever
we're changing is has the intend
Behavior Uh and that we could prove it
um and then it started becoming
interesting imagine it's gaining our
trust when do you think you trust the
agent to
autocommit right ad was one of the first
to put this as a feat feature I don't
know I I think it like The Rao some
horis like I feel safe enough that I can
UT commit but you can always revert if
you wanted to um so that's interesting
because that's the first level of trust
that we're
adding all of these systems are adding
checkpoints roll back do something roll
back um that that is obviously one way
of having a fail safe environment for us
to work in U and allowing it to try
things and see the impact of things in
there as well um another one that I
think it was wind surf had a feature
called lock file so it says like
whatever you do AI you cannot touch this
it's almost like an access control
system for this is what we allow the AI
to do this is what we're not allowing to
do uh you know this is what a com that
we allow automatically this is
not so this brings us to the human
oversight because hey it's gaining our
trust um
but yeah when things really
fail uh things will get fun in
production
right
um what's interesting is that we've been
talking about cognitive load for a long
time now um and I found this like an
interesting way of dealing things left
is the diff view red and green hey I'm
color blind so it's like not that great
for me there's the chat view which is
basically explaining the change it de
but it's quite elaborate and I don't
have the time to read like everything
through that it does on the right we see
something like a condensed view where it
used natural language to condense a
certain piece of the code that it just
explains what the code did so I just
have to read those few lines I don't
have to dig into the whole code thing so
it's reducing cognitive load for me to
be able to review the code faster so
that's like something that will need
more and more as the more and more we're
generating code uh of this um I touched
upon the multiple files the review thing
is like first review this then do that
then go to next that kind of task
oriented breakdown is important because
we cannot Croc everything of all the
files all the time so it's giving us a
focused way of reviewing
things um we might get a fail safe as I
said multiple versions uh choices we can
give it feedback whether we liked it yes
or no what it
generated um obviously we want instant
feedback
and not having to wait like this awesome
video um but that real time aspect is
getting more and more important but the
more we're waiting on the agent the
further away we get from you know
instant having feedback from the
results um this is an example of another
way of dealing with the feedback this is
visualizing and making an image out of
what was generated but more as a diagram
not as a text and it helps us way faster
to understand what was happening instead
of having to read this like S3 bucket
got like this and that so this is uh you
know useful so what we're saying is that
the more maybe the text editor which was
very good at a code editor now becomes
more something as a domain specific
browser we're we're dealing with a
specific problem with specific task for
reviewing so the editors become more
like uh uh what they call moldable uh in
a way that people can extend this in
getting easier reduction of cognitive
load so this was kind of like my summary
of the different pieces that I saw you
know happening in the mix in different F
tools and various pieces uh this was not
a tool Centric uh uh kind of EX
presentation where I say hey you know
tool a is better than b but it gives you
more of a guidance to say hey these
pieces are important this is what I'm
looking for in kind of various tools uh
to get better and um I know it's
um maybe a little bit too early uh as
we're still in transition but I
summarized it as we're moving from
implementation to intent which is kind
of like more of the specification we're
moving from delivering things to more
solution Discovery because now we're
dealing more with finding the right
solution and then it becomes an
implementation we move from dealing with
documentation to dealing with knowledge
hopefully we can stop
micromanaging uh the chat uh and so on
and it becomes more of a self-learning
thing uh and we don't want to have blind
automation as Runway you and then come
back in two days uh but we need to have
a way of guiding it and understanding
this how it goes I think that's it for
the talk um if you like this talk
connect on LinkedIn I'll happily share
the slides uh most of my talks are on my
YouTube Channel if you're
interested um and this is the moment
where you get your phones at thank you
very much